but it means that the closer you are to white on that spectrum, the better off you are. And the closer to black that you are on that spectrum the worse off your are. When we think about how we address problems in this country, we often start from a place of trickle-down justice. So using white folks as the control we say, well, if we make things better for white folks then everybody else is going to get free. But actually it doesn't work that way. We have to address problems at the root,
significa que cuanto más cerca del blanco uno esté en ese espectro, mejor estará. Y que cuanto más cerca del negro uno esté en ese espectro, peor estará. Cuando pensamos la forma de abordar problemas en este país, a menudo empezamos desde un lugar de la justicia por derrame. Así, con los blancos como control, decimos bien, si mejoramos las cosas para los blancos todos saldrán beneficiados. Pero en realidad no funciona así. Tenemos que atacar los problemas de raíz,
and when you deal with what's happening in black communities, it creates an effervescence, right? So a bubble up rather than a trickle down. Let me give an example. When we talk about the wage gap, we often say women make 78 cents to every dollar that a man makes. You all have heard that before. But those are the statistics for white women and white men. The reality is that black women make something like 64 cents to every 78 cents that white women make. When we talk about latinas, it goes down to about 58 cents. If we were to talk about indigenous women, if we were to talk about trans women,
y al lidiar con lo que sucede en las comunidades negras, eso crea una efervescencia, ¿sí? Un burbujeo hacia arriba más que un derrame hacia abajo. Daré un ejemplo. Cuando hablamos de la brecha salarial, a menudo decimos que las mujeres ganan 78 centavos por cada dólar de los hombres. Todos han oído eso antes. Pero esas son estadísticas para mujeres blancas y hombres blancos. La realidad indica que las mujeres negras ganan 64 centavos por cada 78 centavos de las mujeres blancas. Las latinas, ganan 58 centavos. Y si hablamos de mujeres aborígenes, si hablamos de mujeres trans,
it would even go further down. So again, if you deal with those who are the most impacted, everybody has an opportunity to benefit from that, rather than dealing with the folks who are not as impacted, and expecting it to trickle down. MB: So I love the effervescence, bubbling up. AG: Effervescence -- like champagne. (Laughter) MB: Who doesn't love a glass of champagne, right? Champagne and freedom, right? (Laughter) What more could we want, y'all? So you all have been doing this for a minute, and the last few years have been -- well, I can't even imagine, but I'm sure very transformative. And I know that you all have learned a lot about leadership. What do you want to share with these people about what you've learned about leadership? Patrisse, let's start with you. PC: Yeah, we have to invest in black leadership. That's what I've learned the most in the last few years. (Applause) What we've seen is thousands of black people showing up for our lives with very little infrastructure and very little support. I think our work as movement leaders isn't just about our own visibility but rather how do we make the whole visible. How do we not just fight for our individual selves but fight for everybody? And I also think leadership looks like everybody in this audience showing up for black lives. It's not just about coming and watching people on a stage, right? It's about how do you become that leader -- whether it's in your workplace, whether it's in your home -- and believe that the movement for black lives isn't just for us, but it's for everybody. (Applause)
el número sería incluso más bajo. De nuevo, si uno trabaja con los más impactados, todos tendrán la oportunidad de beneficiarse de eso, en vez de trabajar con los menos impactados, y esperar que derrame hacia abajo. MB: Me encanta la efervescencia, el burbujeo hacia arriba. AG: Efervescencia, como el champán. (Risas) MB: ¿A quién no le gusta una copa de champán, ¿no? Champán y libertad, ¿no? (Risas) ¿Qué más podríamos desear, no? Todos lo hemos hecho durante un minuto, y los últimos años han sido... bueno, no puedo ni imaginarlo, pero seguro han sido transformadores. Y sé que todos han aprendido mucho sobre liderazgo. ¿Qué deseas compartir con estas personas sobre lo que has aprendido del liderazgo? Patrisse, empecemos contigo. PC: Sí, tenemos que invertir en el liderazgo negro. Ese es mi mejor aprendizaje en los últimos años. (Aplausos) Hemos visto miles de negros que se presentan en nuestras vidas con muy poca infraestructura y muy poco apoyo. El trabajo como líderes del movimiento no se trata de la propia visibilidad sino de dar visibilidad al conjunto. No de bregar por nosotros, sino de bregar por todos. Y pienso, también, que el liderazgo se parece a este público que se ocupa de las vidas negras. No se trata solo de venir a ver personas en el escenario, ¿no? Se trata de cómo volverse líder, ya sea en el lugar de trabajo, o en el hogar, y de creer que el movimiento por las vidas negras no es solo para nosotros, sino para todos. (Aplausos)
MB: What about you, Opal? OT: So I've been learning a great deal about interdependence. I've been learning about how to trust your team. I've come up with this new mantra after coming back from a three-month sabbatical, which is rare for black women to take who are in leadership, but I felt it was really important for my leadership and for my team to also practice stepping back as well as also sometimes stepping in. And what I learned in this process was that we need to acknowledge that different people contribute different strengths, and that in order for our entire team to flourish, we have to allow them to share and allow them to shine. And so during my sabbatical with the organization that I also work with, I saw our team rise up in my absence. They were able to launch new programs, fundraise. And when I came back, I had to give them a lot of gratitude and praise because they showed me that they truly had my back and that they truly had their own backs. You know, in this process of my sabbatical, I was really reminded of this Southern African philosophy of Ubuntu. I am because you are; you are because I am. And I realized that my own leadership, and the contributions that I'm able to make, is in large part due to the contributions that they make, right? And I have to acknowledge that, and I have to see that, and so my new mantra is, "Keep calm and trust the team." And also, "Keep calm and thank the team." MB: You know, one of the things I feel like I've heard in the context of the Black Lives Matter movement more than anywhere else is about being a leaderful movement, and that's such a beautiful concept, and I think that something that women often bring to the conversation about leadership is really the collective piece. What about you, Alicia? AG: Yeah ... How many of you heard that saying that leadership is lonely? I think that there is an element where leadership is lonely, but I also believe that it doesn't have to be like that. And in order for us to get to that point, I think there's a few things that we need to be doing. So one is we have to stop treating leaders like superheroes. We are ordinary people attempting to do extraordinary things, and so we need to be supported in that way. The other thing that I've learned about leadership is that there's a difference between leadership and celebrities, right? And there's a way in which we've been kind of transformed into celebrities
MB: ¿Qué hay de ti, Opal? OT: He estado aprendiendo mucho sobre la interdependencia. He estado aprendiendo a confiar en el equipo. He encontrado este nuevo mantra después de regresar de un sabático de tres meses, que es raro que tomen las mujeres negras en puestos de liderazgo, pero sentí que era realmente importante para mi liderazgo y para mi equipo practicar también retroceder así como también a veces ingresar. Y en este proceso aprendí que debemos reconocer que distintas personas aportan diferentes puntos fuertes, y que, para que todo el equipo florezca, tenemos que permitirles compartir y permitirles brillar. Por eso durante mi sabático con la organización con la que trabajo, vi a nuestro equipo levantarse en mi ausencia. Pudieron lanzar nuevos programas, recaudar fondos. Y, cuando volví, tuve que darles mucha gratitud y reconocimiento porque me mostraron que contaban con mi apoyo pero que, verdaderamente, tenían sus propias espaldas. Saben, en mi sabático recordé realmente la filosofía sudafricana de ubuntu. "Soy porque tú eres; tú eres porque yo soy". Y me di cuenta de que mi propio liderazgo, y las contribuciones que puedo hacer, se deben en gran parte a las contribuciones que ellos hacen, ¿no? Y tengo que reconocer que, y tengo que ver que, por eso mi nuevo mantra es: "Mantén la calma y confía en el equipo". Y también: "Mantén la calma y agradece al equipo". MB: Sabes, una de las cosas que siento que he escuchado en el contexto del movimiento Black Lives Matter más que en otro lugar es un movimiento de co-liderazgo, y ese es un concepto muy hermoso, y creo que algo que las mujeres a menudo aportan a la conversación sobre liderazgo es realmente la pieza colectiva. ¿Qué hay de ti, Alicia? AG: Sí... ¿Cuántos de Uds. han oído decir que el liderazgo es solitario? Creo que hay un elemento donde el liderazgo es solitario, pero también creo que no tiene por qué ser así. Y para llegar a ese punto, creo que hay algunas cosas que debemos hacer. Una es que tenemos que dejar de tratar a los líderes como superhéroes. Somos gente común que trata de hacer cosas poco comunes, por eso necesitamos apoyo. Otra cosa que aprendí del liderazgo es que hay una diferencia entre ser líder y ser celebridad, ¿no? En cierto modo nos hemos convertido en celebridades
rather than people who are trying to solve a problem. And the way that we treat celebrities is very fickle, right? We like them one day, we don't like what they're wearing the next day, and all of a sudden we have issues, right? So we need to stop deifying leaders so that more people will step into leadership. Lots of people are terrified to step into leadership because of how much scrutiny they receive and how brutal we are with leaders. And then the last thing that I've learned about leadership is that it's really easy to be a leader when everybody likes you. But it's hard to be a leader when you have to make hard choices and when you have to do what's right, even though people are not going to like you for it. And so in that way, I think another way that we can support leaders is to struggle with us, but struggle with us politically, not personally. We can have disagreements without being disagreeable, but it's important for us to sharpen each other, so that we all can rise. MB: That's beautiful, thank you. (Applause) So you all are doing work that forces you to face some brutal, painful realities on a daily basis. What gives you hope and inspires you in that context? PC: I am hopeful for black futures. And I say that because we live in a society that's so obsessed with black death. We have images of our death on the TV screen, on our Twitter timelines, on our Facebook timelines, but what if instead we imagine black life? We imagine black people living and thriving. And that -- that inspires me. OT: What inspires me these days are immigrants. Immigrants all over the world who are doing the best that they can to make a living, to survive and also to thrive. Right now there are over 244 million people who aren't living in their country of origin. This is a 40 percent increase since the year 2000. So what this tells me is that the disparities across the globe are only getting worse. Yet there are people who are finding the strength and wherewithal to travel, to move, to eke out a better living for themselves and to provide for their families and their loved ones. And some of these people who are immigrants
en vez de personas que tratan de resolver un problema. Y tratamos a las celebridades de manera un poco lábil, ¿no? Un día nos gustan, al otro día no nos gusta lo que llevan puesto, y de repente tenemos problemas, ¿no? Por eso debemos dejar de endiosar a los líderes para que más personas asuman el liderazgo. Mucha gente está aterrorizada de saltar al liderazgo por el escrutinio excesivo que reciben y por lo brutales que somos con los líderes. Y luego lo último que he aprendido sobre el liderazgo es que es fácil ser líder cuando le gustas a todo el mundo. Pero es difícil ser líder si debes tomar decisiones difíciles y si tienes que hacer lo correcto, aun cuando no le gustes a la gente justamente por eso. Y así, de esa manera, pienso en otra manera para apoyar a los líderes es sumarse a nuestra lucha, sumarse a nuestra lucha políticamente, no de forma personal. Podemos tener desacuerdos sin ser desagradables, pero es importante para nosotros que nos potenciemos mutuamente, para que todos podamos levantarnos. MB: Eso es hermoso, gracias. (Aplausos) Uds. están haciendo un trabajo que las obliga a enfrentar realidades brutales, dolorosas, a diario. ¿Qué les da esperanza y las inspira en ese contexto? PC: Tengo esperanza por los futuros negros. Y lo digo porque vivimos en una sociedad obsesionada por la muerte negra. Tenemos imágenes de nuestra muerte en la pantalla de TV, en las líneas de tiempo de Twitter, o en las de Facebook, pero ¿qué tal si imaginamos la vida negra? Imaginamos a los negros vivos y prósperos. Y eso... eso me inspira. OT: Lo que me inspira estos días son los inmigrantes. Inmigrantes en todo el mundo que están haciendo lo mejor que pueden para ganarse la vida, sobrevivir y también para prosperar. Ahora mismo hay más de 244 millones de personas que no viven en su país de origen. Se trata de un aumento del 40 % desde el año 2000. Eso me dice que las disparidades en todo el mundo solo están empeorando. Sin embargo, hay personas que encuentran la fuerza y los medios para viajar, para moverse, para conseguir una vida mejor para ellos mismos y para sus familias y seres queridos. Y algunas de estas personas son inmigrantes
are also undocumented.
y también indocumentados.
They're unauthorized. And they inspire me even more because although our society is telling them, you're not wanted, you're not needed here, and they're highly vulnerable and subject to abuse, to wage theft, to exploitation and xenophobic attacks, many of them are also beginning to organize in their communities. And what I'm seeing is that there's also an emerging network of black, undocumented people who are resisting the framework, and resisting the criminalization of their existence. And that to me is incredibly powerful
No están autorizados. Y me inspiran aún más porque aunque nuestra sociedad le está diciendo Uds. no son queridos, no los necesitamos aquí, y son muy vulnerables y sujeto a abuso, a robo de sueldo, a explotación y a ataques xenófobos, muchos de ellos también están empezando a organizarse en sus comunidades. Y estoy viendo que también hay una red emergente de la población negra, indocumentada, que se resiste al marco, y resiste la criminalización de su existencia. Y eso para mí es increíblemente poderoso
and inspires me every singe day. MB: Thank you. Alicia? AG: So we know that young people are the present and the future, but what inspires me are older people who are becoming transformed in the service of this movement. We all know that as you get older,
y me inspira cada día. MB: Gracias. ¿Alicia? AG: Sabemos que los jóvenes son el presente y el futuro, pero me inspiran las personas mayores que se están transformando al servicio de este movimiento. Sabemos que conforme uno envejece,
you get a little more entrenched in your ways. It's happening to me, I know that's right.
se atrinchera un poco más en sus formas. Me ocurre a mí, sé que eso es correcto.
But I'm so inspired when I see people who have a way that they do things, have a way that they think about the world, and they're courageous enough to be open to listening to what the experiences are of so many of us who want to live in world that's just and want to live in a world that's equitable. And I'm also inspired by the actions that I'm seeing older people taking in service of this movement. I'm inspired by seeing older people step into their own power and leadership and say, "I'm not passing a torch, I'm helping you light the fire." (Applause) MB: I love that -- yes. So in terms of action, I think that it is awesome to sit here and be able to listen to you all, and to have our minds open and shift, but that's not going to get black people free. So if you had one thing you would like this audience and the folks who are watching around the world to actually do, what would that be? AG: OK, two quick ones. One, call the White House. The water protectors are being forcibly removed from the camp that they have set up to defend what keeps us alive. And that is intricately related to black lives. So definitely call the White House and demand that they stop doing that. There are tanks and police officers arresting every single person there as we speak. (Applause) The second thing that you can do
Pero me inspira ver a la gente que tiene una forma de hacer cosas, que tiene una forma de pensar el mundo, y son valientes como para estar abiertos a escuchar las experiencias de tantos de nosotros que queremos vivir en un mundo justo y queremos vivir en un mundo equitativo. Y también me inspiran las acciones de las personas mayores que veo al servicio de este movimiento. Me inspira ver gente mayor asumir su propio poder y liderazgo y decir: "No estoy pasando una antorcha, estoy ayudando a encender el fuego". (Aplausos) MB: Me encanta eso, sí. En términos de acción, creo que es increíble sentarse aquí y poder escucharlas a Uds., y tener nuestras mentes abiertas y flexibles, pero eso no va a liberar a las personas negras. Así que si tuvieran algo que quisieran que este público y quienes están mirando en el mundo hicieran, ¿qué sería? AG: Bien, dos rápidas. Una, llamar a la Casa Blanca. Están eliminando los protectores de agua por la fuerza del campamento que han montado para defender lo que nos mantiene vivos. Y eso está relacionado intrincadamente con las vidas negras. Definitivamente, llamen a la Casa Blanca y exijan que dejen de hacer eso. Hay tanques y agentes de policía deteniendo a cada persona allí mientras hablamos. (Aplausos) La segunda cosa que pueden hacer
is to join something. Be a part of something. There are groups, collectives -- doesn't have to be a non-profit, you know what I mean? But there are groups that are doing work in our communities right now to make sure that black lives matter so all lives matter. Get involved; don't sit on your couch and tell people what you think they should be doing. Go do it with us. MB: Do you guys want to add anything? That's good? All right. So -- And I think that the joining something, like if you feel like there's not something where you are, start it. AG: Start it. MB: These conversations that we're having, have those conversations with somebody else.
es unirse a algo. Sean parte de algo. Hay grupos, colectivos... no tiene que ser una ONG, ¿saben a lo que me refiero? Pero hay grupos que están trabajando en nuestras comunidades ahora para que las vidas negras importen así todas las vidas importan. Participen; no se sienten en el sofá y digan qué piensan que se debe hacer. Háganlo con nosotros. MB: ¿Quieres agregar algo? ¿Está bien? Todo bien. Así que... Y pienso que al sumarse a algo, si sienten que no tienen a qué sumarse, creen algo. AG: Créenlo. MB: Estas conversaciones que entablamos, conversen de esto con otras personas.
And then instead of just letting it be a talk that you had, actually decide to start something. OT: That's right. MB: I mean, that's what you all did. You started something, and look what's happened. Thank you all so much for being here with us today. OT: Thank you. (Applause)
Y en vez de dejar que sea una charla que tuvieron, decidan crear algo. OT: Correcto. MB: Digo, es lo que hicieron Uds. Crearon algo y vieron qué pasaba. Muchas gracias a todas por estar aquí con nosotros hoy. OT: Gracias. (Aplausos)